<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>http://www.lambdaladies.com</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.lambdaladies.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2015 00:34:06 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2015 00:34:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>

    
    
    <item>
      <title>Interview with Chris Martens, Programming Languages Ph.D Candidate</title>
      <link>http://www.lambdaladies.com/2014/09/02/interview-with-chris-martens/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 08:37:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://www.lambdaladies.com/2014/09/02/interview-with-chris-martens</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Learn more about Chris Martens&amp;#39;s work on logic programming, games, and forging new connections in computational creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Who are you and what do you do?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/%7Ecmartens/&quot;&gt;Chris Martens&lt;/a&gt;, or chrisamaphone everywhere on the internet, and for the last ~6 years i&amp;#39;ve been a computer science grad student at CMU!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tell us about what you&amp;#39;re studying.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve been studying in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/Groups/pop/pop.html&quot;&gt;POP (Principles of Programming)&lt;/a&gt; group. We&amp;#39;re all working on programming languages in some capacity, usually with a types/logic angle. I&amp;#39;ve done a couple of projects on dependent types and proof assistants, and now I&amp;#39;m working on a logic programming language for my thesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;#39;s logic programming?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logic programming is a way of interpreting a collection of logical assertions as a program! In the wild you might encounter Prolog or (more practically) database systems like SQL -- the concept of a &amp;quot;query&amp;quot; comes from the idea of asking a question in logic, &amp;quot;is the formula A provable,&amp;quot; and then having your program execute as a search for a proof of A (there might be multiple proofs.) At its core, a logic program interpreter is &amp;quot;just&amp;quot; a theorem prover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What kind of problems would you say logic programming languages are well suited for?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d say any time you&amp;#39;re thinking primarily about the &lt;em&gt;relationships&lt;/em&gt; between data, logic programming might be a good fit. I think their most common use is in databases, but that&amp;#39;s actually the one I&amp;#39;m least familiar with. I&amp;#39;ve used logic programming most as a tool for expressing formal systems -- things like languages and logics that you can describe naturally through inference rules. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Systems like...say, games?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heh. Yes! I was trying to figure out a good segue to that...my thesis project started with noticing that logic programs might be a good way to represent the rules of games. Games aren&amp;#39;t always thought of as formal systems, and some argue that doing so can impede design. But on the other hand, I like to think of a formal description as something that sits nicely at the boundary between human and computer. As a human, you can think more in terms of game rules instead of &amp;quot;how exactly am I going to represent all these data structures and get good performance&amp;quot;, but you still have something you can execute &amp;amp; play with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Is your thesis language specifically related to games?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yep! I started out trying to make it really broad and talk about &amp;quot;interactive systems&amp;quot; in general, but having a really specific application has helped me make a lot more progress...especially an application that I care about independently from PL stuff, and one that a lot of people can relate to and talk about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tell us a little bit about the language itself and in what ways games/interactive systems have shaped it.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The language I&amp;#39;m starting with is one that I got super into after my advisor Frank Pfenning, who coauthored the language, taught a class that used it. It&amp;#39;s called Celf, and it still lives in a tiny little academic corner with zero documentation, but you can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/clf/celf&quot;&gt;on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. My language will basically be talking Celf, skimming off a simple subset of the language, and adding capacity for interactive execution, along with some special mechanisms for control flow between program components. My design has also been inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;http://inform7.com/&quot;&gt;Inform 7&lt;/a&gt;, a popular engine for making text games. It&amp;#39;s basically a logic programming language already... but as I&amp;#39;ve used it I&amp;#39;ve been more convinced I need to make a language based on Celf!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;OK, so at this point I have questions about PL design and also about games...walk north for PL design, and open the door for games?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; open door&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tell us about a game you&amp;#39;ve made!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I mostly make interactive fiction (IF), except my IF is weird because I don&amp;#39;t really like writing fiction -- I tend to just make these weird little systems that happen to get rendered in text. But recently I&amp;#39;ve been into a 2D games engine called &lt;a href=&quot;http://love2d.org/&quot;&gt;LÖVE2D&lt;/a&gt;, which I used to make a game called &amp;quot;QWOP training run&amp;quot;
and it kind of has the structure of IF, in that i&amp;#39;m telling a branching story (autobiographical) through it, but it&amp;#39;s superficially just an arcade-like running game (you mash keys to run faster.) The branching points in the story are represented by geographical branching points in the running route. You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/folderview?id=0B1HJXoh3BOUbU21LcWZiWGVyZ0E&amp;amp;usp=drive_web&quot;&gt;check it out yourself&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Are you a gamer? What draws you to game design?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I dunno if I&amp;#39;m a gamer. I feel like there&amp;#39;s a lot of gatekeeping around that term, so I prefer to stay away from it. But I really enjoy what people who approach games as an artform can manage to do with it. It&amp;#39;s a form of expression where your audience participates in the experience, so you can use that to tell stories, or to communicate systems, including social ones. A lot of what I like about games is the same as what I like about math. It&amp;#39;s stuff you express in rules, and the rules &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; things - they contain this world that (if designed well) will keep surprising you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Do you have a strong math background?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No and yes. I don&amp;#39;t have a lot of what I think of as &amp;quot;standard math&amp;quot; -- calculus, real analysis, linear algebra... but I&amp;#39;ve learned a lot of algebra and category theory over the last few years, which is pretty fun. I was lucky enough to be at CMU where Steve Awodey was teaching category theory, sort of at the forefront of a new wave of mathematical foundations, a few years before the Haskell community exploded and everyone was talking about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Speaking of! Do you consider yourself part of any computing &amp;quot;communities&amp;quot;?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community is tricky for me (maybe just as tricky as for everyone). It seems like academics are expected to find community w/their collaborators &amp;amp; colleagues, but it never felt easy for me to fit into that. And a lot of non-academic groups tend to focus on one specific language, which also doesn&amp;#39;t feel right to me. So that leaves online communities, and I guess the sort of ad-hoc computing communities that form on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/chrisamaphone&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; are the ones I feel most active on. People say Twitter is no good for discussion, but I&amp;#39;ve had some pretty constructive academic &amp;amp; programming discussions on there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Thoughts/feelings about academia vs games programming you do?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Academic CS and the kinds of games communities I follow seem like they&amp;#39;re about as far apart on the &amp;quot;tech&amp;quot; spectrum as they can get. Within games communities, &amp;quot;academia&amp;quot; often refers to humanities or arts programs -- or maybe this is just my IF predisposition, &amp;#39;cause a lot of those folks come from &amp;quot;electronic literature.&amp;quot; And when they think of computer science&amp;#39;s relevance to games it&amp;#39;s usually &amp;quot;AI,&amp;quot; for various values of things under that umbrella (conversation bots, NLP, social modeling) rather than programming languages (PL). I&amp;#39;m hoping my research will take me in directions -- either by doing more academia or getting hired by more experimental games companies -- that can bridge the ideas. I think PL, functional programming, etc. have a lot to offer digital arts &amp;amp; computational creativity, because we think a lot about &lt;em&gt;interfaces&lt;/em&gt; to expression. The cultures are just so different. I wanna help that change!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Erlang User Conference in Stockholm on June 9-10, 2014</title>
      <link>http://www.lambdaladies.com/2014/04/12/erlang-user-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2014 12:13:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://www.lambdaladies.com/2014/04/12/erlang-user-conference</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The largest European conference dedicated to Erlang -- the functional language behind WhatsApp&amp;#39;s success -- will feature more than 50 talks on open-source applications, products and war stories from the community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The keynotes will be delivered by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/codemiller&quot;&gt;Katie Miller&lt;/a&gt;, Lambda Ladies Co-Founder and OpenShift Developer Advocate, and by Stuart Bailey, CTO of Infoblox. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speakers include: &amp;#39;Seven Languages in Seven Weeks&amp;#39; author &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/redrapids&quot;&gt;Bruce Tate&lt;/a&gt;, co-designer of Haskell and QuickCheck &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rjmh&quot;&gt;John Hughes&lt;/a&gt;, O&amp;#39;Reilly author Erik Stenman, Rakuten lead technologist Yosuke Hara, Feuerlabs Co-founder and Developer Advocate Ulf Wiger and many more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early Bird rates end on 9 May. Use the code &amp;#39;LambdaLadies15&amp;#39; to get a 15 per cent discount on top of the Early Bird price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more info go to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.erlang-factory.com/conference/EUC2014/&quot;&gt;the Erlang User Conference website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Lambda Ladies story</title>
      <link>http://www.lambdaladies.com/2013/05/04/the-lambda-ladies-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2013 07:53:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://www.lambdaladies.com/2013/05/04/the-lambda-ladies-story</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lambda Ladies began in March 2013 when five women who came together online to collaborate on a functional programming conference presentation decided to take the camaraderie they had shared to a wider group. Those software engineers were Rachel Reese, Kelsey Innis, Dana Contreras, Susan Potter and myself, Katie Miller. Although we hadn’t met in person and were far apart geographically, we found we had a shared experience — being one of few women in our local functional programming (FP) communities. We would all like to see more girls and women embracing FP so we decided to do something to encourage that by starting this group. There are focused groups for women using Python, Ruby on Rails, Java, Drupal, PHP and many other languages, frameworks and technologies, but there didn’t seem to be anything for those interested in FP, until now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why have a group for girls/women? Doesn’t this encourage segregation?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not our intention, nor has it been my experience from my exposure to other women’s tech groups. We are active members of our local functional programming user groups and we would encourage other women to join us in this. I certainly don’t want to be the only regular female attendee of my local FP group forever. Although I am comfortable attending as the only woman, I recognise that others may find this intimidating and would not dare to draw attention to themselves by asking a question at one of our meetings. The Lambda Ladies group is a non-threatening environment where women, especially beginners, can ask questions and grow in their knowledge. It would be my hope that this process can help them to gain confidence to then go out and participate in other groups. Even for those women who aren’t beginners, it is valuable to have support, be able to talk about shared experiences and challenges, and have the opportunity to mentor others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Are men allowed to join?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discussed the idea of allowing supportive males to join Lambda Ladies and found group members had mixed opinions. We want to keep the environment non-threatening to all, so at this stage, membership is only open to those who identify as women. That said, we still appreciate help and support from men, and may well include male in any events we might hold in the future. Although the Google Group part of the site is closed, other sections we are developing will be open to all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How successful has the group been so far?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first thought of the idea of starting a Lambda Ladies group a year or so ago, I went no further with it because I was afraid I might be the only member. How wrong I was. In a little over a month, Lambda Ladies has grown to more than 100 members and there is a healthy amount of discussion in the group, including conversations about highly technical topics way over my head. This is an extremely encouraging start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What’s so good about functional programming?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming in the functional style makes you better able to reason about the behaviour of your code and enables you to write more succinct and modular programs. It teaches you to think about problems in a different way, and it’s also heaps of fun. The FP paradigm has been gaining popularity, so it’s worth knowing about as the concepts tend to pop up no matter what language you are using. Several FP-oriented languages have emerged in the past 10 years (eg: Scala, F#, Clojure, LINQ) and existing languages have added FP features, such as C# and PHP (first-class functions), Python (lambda, filter and map) and Java (lambda expressions are coming in Java 8).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;So did the conference presentation go ahead?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will find out this month if our conference proposal for the Grace Hopper Celebration has been accepted. However, even if it is not, it’s been a worthwhile endeavour because it brought the five of us together and sparked the creation of Lambda Ladies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    

  </channel> 
</rss>